<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Maiesties speach in the Starre-Chamber the XX. of Ivne. anno 1616.</title>
            <title>Speeches. 1616-06-20</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72433</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898411_176995</idno>
  <idno type="VID">176995</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264169867</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 14397.7</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S106494</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99898411e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72433)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176995)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 740:3, 2067:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Maiesties speach in the Starre-Chamber the XX. of Ivne. anno 1616.</title>
                  <title>Speeches. 1616-06-20</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[62] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Robert Barker, printer to the Kings most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1616]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In this edition leaf A3r catchword: "Giue"; 3 asterisks at end of text--STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 14398.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴ (-A1, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Judges --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1603-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176995:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176995:1"/>
            <p>HIS MAIESTIES SPEACH IN <hi>THE STARRE-Chamber,</hi> THE XX. OF IVNE. ANNO 1616.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Jmprinted at London by</hi> RO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BERT BARKER, Printer to the Kings most Excellent Maiestie.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:176995:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176995:2"/>
            <head>HIS MAIESTIES SPEACH IN THE STARRE-CHAMBER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Iue thy Judgements to the King, O God, and thy righteousnes to the Kings sonne.</hi> These bee the first wordes of one of the Psalmes of the Kingly Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> whereof the literall sense runnes vpon him and his sonne <hi>Salomon,</hi> and the mystical sense vpon GOD, and CHRIST his eternall Sonne: but they are both so wouen together, as some parts are, and can onely be properly applied vnto GOD and CHRIST, and other parts vnto <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Salomon,</hi> as this Verse,
<pb facs="tcp:176995:3"/>
               <hi>Giue thy Iudgement to the King, O God, and thy righteousnesse to the Kings sonne,</hi> cannot be properly spoken of any, but of <hi>Dauid</hi> and his sonne; because it is said, <hi>Giue thy Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp;c.</hi> Now God cannot giue to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe. In another part of the same Psalme, where it is said, that <hi>Righteousnes shall flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish, and abundance of Peace, as long as the Moone endureth,</hi> it signifieth eternitie, and cannot bee properly applied but to GOD and CHRIST: But both senses, aswell literall as mysticall, serue to Kings for imitation, and especially to Christian Kings: for Kings sit in the Throne of GOD, and they themselues are called Gods.</p>
            <p>And therefore all good Kings in their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, must imitate God and his Christ, in being iust and righteous; <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> in being godly and wise: To be wise, is vnderstood, able to discerne, able to iudge others: To be godly is, that the fountaine be pure whence the streames proceed: for what auailes it though all his workes bee godly, if they proceed not from godlinesse: To be righteous, is to a mans selfe: To bee
<pb facs="tcp:176995:3"/>iust, is towards others: But Iustice in a King auailes not, vnlesse it be with a cleane heart: for except he be Righteous, aswell as Iust, he is no good King: and what euer iustice hee doeth; except hee doeth it for Iustice sake, and out of the purenesse of his owne heart, neither from priuate ends, vaine-glory, or any other by-respects of his owne, all such Iustice is vnrighteousnes, and no trew Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice. From this imitation of GOD and CHRIST, in whose Throne wee sit, the gouernment of all Common-wealths, and especially Monarchies, hath bene from the beginning setled and established. Kings are properly Iudges and Iudgement proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belongs to them from GOD: for Kings sit in the Throne of GOD, and thence all Iudgement is deriued.</p>
            <p>In all well setled Monarchies, where Law is established formally and orderly, there Iudgement is deferred from the King to his subordinate Magistrates; not that the King takes it from himselfe, but giues it vnto them: So it comes not to them <hi>Priuatiuè,</hi> but <hi>Cumulatiuè,</hi> as the Schoolemen speake.
<pb facs="tcp:176995:4"/>The ground is ancient, euer sithence that Counsell which <hi>Iethro</hi> gaue to <hi>Moses:</hi> for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that <hi>Moses</hi> had gouerned a long time, in his owne person, the burthen grew so great, hauing none to helpe him, as his father in law comming to visite him, found him so cumbred with ministring of Iustice, that neither the people were satisfied, nor he well able to performe it; Therefore by his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, Iudges were deputed for easier questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the greater and more profound were left to <hi>Moses:</hi> And according to this establishment, all Kings that haue had a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall gouernement, especially Christian Kings in all aages haue gouerned their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, though after a diuers maner.</p>
            <p>This Deputation is after one maner in <hi>France,</hi> after another here, and euen my owne Kingdomes differ in this point of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment: for <hi>Scotland</hi> differs both from <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England</hi> herein; but all agree in this, (I speake of such Kingdomes or States where the formalitie of law hath place) that the King that sits in Gods Throne, onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes subalterne Iudges, and he deputes not
<pb facs="tcp:176995:4"/>one but a number (for no one subalterne Iudges mouth makes Law) and their office is to interprete Law, and administer Iustice. But as to the number of them, the forme of gouernement, the manner of interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the distinction of Benches, the diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie of Courts; these varie according to the varietie of gouernement, and institution of diuers Kings: So this ground I lay, that the feate of Iudgement is properly Gods, and Kings are Gods Vicegerents; and by Kings Iudges are deputed vnder them, to beare the burden of gouernement, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the first example of <hi>Moses</hi> by the aduice of <hi>Iethro,</hi> and sithence practised by <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Salomon,</hi> the wisest Kings that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer were; which is in this Psalme so inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laced, that as the first verse cannot be apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed properly but to <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Salomon,</hi> in the wordes, <hi>Giue thy iudgement to the King,</hi> &amp;c. So the other place in the same Psalme, <hi>Righteousnesse shall flourish, and abundance of peace shall remaine as long as the Moone endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth,</hi> properly signifieth the eternitie of CHRIST. This I speake to shew what a
<pb facs="tcp:176995:5"/>neere coniunction there is betweene God and the King vpward, and the King and his Iudges downewards: for the same coniunction that is betweene God and the King vpward; the same coniunction is betweene the King and his Iudges downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
            <p>As Kings borrow their power from God, so Iudges from Kings: And as Kings are to accompt to God, so Iudges vnto God and Kings; and both Kings and Iudges by imitation, haue two qualities from God and his Christ, and two qualities from <hi>Dauid</hi> and his <hi>Salomon.</hi> Iudgement and Righteousnes, from God and Christ: Godlines and Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Salomon.</hi> And as no King can discharge his accompt to God, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse he make conscience not to alter, but to declare and establish the wil of God: So Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges cannot discharge their accompts to Kings, vnlesse they take the like care, not to take vpon them to make law, but ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether after a deliberate consultation, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what the Law is; For as Kings are sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto GODS Law, so they to mans
<pb facs="tcp:176995:5"/>Law. It is the Kings Office to protect and settle the trew interpretation of the Law of God within his Dominions: And it is the Iudges Office to interprete the Law of the King, whereto themselues are also subiect.</p>
            <p>Hauing now performed this ancient Prouerbe, <hi>A Ioue principium,</hi> which though it was spoken by a Pagan, yet it is good and holy: I am now to come to my particular Errand, for which I am here this day; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I must handle two parts: First, the reason why I haue not these fourteene yeeres, si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence my Coronation vntill now, satisfied a great many of my louing subiects, who I know haue had a great expectation, and as it were a longing, like them that are with child, to heare me speake in this place, where my Predecessors haue often sitten, and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially King <hi>Henry</hi> the seuenth; from whom, as diuers wayes before, I am lineally descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and that doubly to this Crowne; and as I am neerest descended of him, so doe I desire to follow him in his best actions.</p>
            <p>The next part is the reason, Why I am now come: The cause that made mee ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staine,
<pb facs="tcp:176995:6"/>was this: When I came into <hi>England</hi> although I was an olde <hi>King,</hi> past middle aage, and practised in gouernment euersi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence I was twelue yeeres olde; yet being here a stranger in gouernment, though not in blood, because my breeding was in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Kingdome; I resolued therfore with <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras</hi> to keep silence seuen yeres, &amp; learne my selfe the lawes of this Kingdome, before I would take vpon mee to teach them vnto others: When this Apprentiship was ended, then another impediment came, which was in the choice of that cause, that should first bring mee hither. I expected some great cause to make my first entry vpon: For I thought that hauing abstained so long, it should bee a worthy matter that should bring me hither. Now euery cause must be great or small: In small causes I thought it disgraceful to come, hauing beene so long absent: In great causes, they must be either betwixt the <hi>King</hi> and some of his Subiects, or betwixt Subiect and Subiect.</p>
            <p>In a cause where my selfe was concerned, I was loath to come, because men should
<pb facs="tcp:176995:6"/>not thinke I did come for my owne priuate, either Prerogatiue or profit; or for any other by-respect: And in that I will alwaies abide the triall of men and Angels, neuer to haue had any particular end, in that which is the Maine of all things, <hi>Iustice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a great cause also betweene partie and party, great in respect either of the question, or value of the thing, my comming might seeme, as it were obliquely, to bee in fauour of one party, and for that cause this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellour, or that Courtier might bee thought to mooue me to come hither; And a meane cause was nor worthy of mee, especially for my first entrance: So, lacke of choise in both respects, kept mee off till now: And now hauing passed a double apprentiship of twice seuen yeeres, I am come hither to speake vnto you. And next as to the reasons of my comming at this time, they are these:</p>
            <p>I haue obserued in the time of my whole Reigne here, and my double Apprenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, diuers things fallen out in the Iudica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures here at <hi>Westminster</hi> Hall, that I thought required and vrged a reformation at my
<pb facs="tcp:176995:7"/>hands; whereupon I resolued with my selfe, that I could not more fitly begin a reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then here to make an open declaration of my meaning. I remember Christs saying, <hi>My sheepe heare my voyce,</hi> and so I assure my selfe, my people will most willingly heare the voice of me, their owne Shepheard and King; whereupon I tooke this occasion in mine owne person here in this Seate of Iudgement, not iudicially, but declaratorily and openly to giue those directions, which, at other times by piece-meale, I haue deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to some of you in diuers lesse publike places; but now will put it vp in all your audience, where I hope it shall bee trewly caried, and cannot be mistaken, as it might haue bene when it was spoken more priuate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. I will for order sake take mee to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode of the number of Three, the number of perfection, and vpon that number distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute all I haue to declare to you.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irst I am to giue a charge to my selfe: for a king, or iudge vnder a king, that first giues not a good charge to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe,
<pb facs="tcp:176995:7"/>wil neuer be able to giue a good charge to his inferiors; for as I haue said, Good ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers cannot flow but frō good springs; if the fountaine be impure, so must the riuers be.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to the Iudges: And thirdly, to the Auditory, and the rest of the inferiour ministers of Iustice.</p>
            <p>First I protest to you all, in all your audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, here sitting in the seate of Iustice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing vnto God, and now by right fallen vnto me, that I haue resolued, as Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in Maiority followeth Baptisme in minoritie; so now after many yeeres, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new my promise &amp; oath made at my Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation concerning Iustice, and the promise therein for maintenance of the Law of the land. And I protest in Gods presence, my care hath euer bene to keepe my conscience cleare in all the points of my Oath, taken at my Coronation, so farre as humane frailtie may permit me, or my knowledge informe mee, I speake in point of Iustice and Law; For Religion, I hope I am reasonably well; knowen already: I meane therefore of Law and Iustice; and for Law, I meane the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb facs="tcp:176995:8"/>Law of the land, according to which the King gouernes, and by which the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are gouerned. For the Common Law, you can all beare me witnes, I neuer pressed alteration of it in Parliament; but on the contrary, when I endeuored most an Vnion reall, as was already in my person, my desire was to conforme the Lawes of <hi>Scotland</hi> to the Law of <hi>England,</hi> and not the Law of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to the Law of <hi>Scotland;</hi> and so the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesie to bee trew of my wise Grandfather <hi>Henry</hi> the 7. who fortold that the lesser king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by marriage, would follow the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and not the greater the lesser: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore married his eldest daughter <hi>Margaret</hi> to <hi>Iames</hi> the fourth, my great Grandfather.</p>
            <p>It was a foolish Querke of some Iudges, who helde that the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> could not vnite <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England</hi> by the name of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> but that it would make an alteration of the Lawes, though I am since come to that knowledge, that an Acte of Parliament can doe greater won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: And that old wise man the Treasourer <hi>Burghley</hi> was wont to say, Hee knew not
<pb facs="tcp:176995:8"/>what an Acte of Parliament could not doe in <hi>England;</hi> for my intention was alwayes to effect Vnion by vniting <hi>Scotland</hi> to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and not <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Scotland:</hi> For I euer meant, being euer resolued, that this Law should continue in this Kingdome, and two things mooued me thereunto; One is, that in matter of Policie and State, you shall neuer see any thing anciently and maturely established, but by Innouation or alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it is worse then it was, I meane not by purging of it from corruptions, and resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it to the ancient integritie; An other reason was, I was sworne to maintaine the Law of the land, and therefore I had bene periured if I had altered it; And this I speake to roote out the conceit and misapprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, if it bee in any heart, that I would change, damnifie, vilifie, or suppresse the Law of this Land. GOD is my Iudge I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer meant it; And this confirmation I make before you all.</p>
            <p>To this I ioyne the point of Iustice, which I call <hi>Vnicuique suum tribuere.</hi> All my Councell, and Iudges, dead and aliue
<pb facs="tcp:176995:9"/>can, and could beare me witnesse, how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall I haue bene in declaring of Law. And where it hath concerned mee in my owne inheritance, I haue as willingly sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted my interest to the Law, as any my Subiects could doe, and it becomes mee so to doe, to giue example to others: much lesse then, will I be partiall to others, where I am not to my selfe. And so resolue your selues, Iustice with mee may bee moderated in point of clemencie: for no Iustice can bee without Mercie. But in matters of Iustice to giue euery man his owne, to bee blinde without eyes of partialitie; This is my full resolution.</p>
            <p>I vsed to say when I was in <hi>Scotland,</hi> if any man mooued mee to delay Iustice, that it was against the Office of a King so to doe; But when any made suit to hasten Iustice, I told them I had rather graunt fourtie of these suits, then one of the other: This was alwayes my custome and shalbe euer, with Gods leaue.</p>
            <p>Now what I haue spoken of Law and Iustice, I meane by the Law kept in her
<pb facs="tcp:176995:9"/>owne bounds: For I vnderstand the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the King, and Subiects in this land, must bee determined by the Common Law, &amp;c; and that is, by the Law set downe in our forefathers time, expounded by lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men diuers times after in the declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie Comments, called <hi>Responsa Prudentum;</hi> Or els by Statute Law, set downe by Act of Parliament, as occasion serues: By this I do not seclude all other Lawes of <hi>England;</hi> but this is the Law of inheritance in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>There is another Law, of all Lawes free and supreame, which is GODS LAVV: And by this all Common and municipall Lawes must be gouerned: And except they haue dependance vpon this Law, they are vniust and vnlawfull.</p>
            <p>When I speake of that Law, I onely giue this touch, That that Law in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome hath bene too much neglected, and Churchmen too much had in contempt, I must speake trewth, Great men, Lords, Iudges, and people of all degrees from the highest to the lowest, haue too much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned
<pb facs="tcp:176995:10"/>them: And GOD will not blesse vs in our owne Lawes, if we doe not reuerence and obey GODS LAW; which cannot be, except the interpreters of it be respected and reuerenced.</p>
            <p>And it is a signe of the latter dayes draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on; euen the contempt of the Church, and of the Gouernours and Teachers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of now in the Church of ENGLAND, which I say in my conscience, of any Church that euer I read or knew of, present or past, is most pure, and neerest the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue and Apostolicall Church in Doctrine and Discipline, and is sureliest founded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the word of God, of any Church in Christendome.</p>
            <p>Next vnto this Law is the Law of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which God forbid should bee barred, and that for two causes: One, because it is a Law to satisfie strangers, which will not so well hold themselues satisfied with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther municipall Lawes: An other, to satisfie our owne Subiects in matters of Piracie, Marriage, Wills, and things of like nature: That Law I diuide into Ciuill and Canon;
<pb facs="tcp:176995:10"/>And this Law hath bene so much encroa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vpon, sithence my comming to the Crowne, and so had in contempt, that yong men are discouraged from studying, and the rest weary of their liues that doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse it, and would bee glad to seeke any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther craft.</p>
            <p>So, speaking of the Common Law, I meane the Common Law kept within her owne limits, and not derogating from these other Lawes, which by long custome haue bene rooted here, first, the LAW OF GOD and his Church, and next, the Law Ciuill and Canon, which in many cases can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be wanting.</p>
            <p>To conclude this charge which I giue my selfe, I professe to maintaine all the points of mine Oath, especially in Lawes, and of Lawes, especially the Common-Law.</p>
            <p>And as to maintaine it, so to purge it; for else it cannot be maintained: and especially to purge it from two corruptions, Incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie and Noueltie: Incertaintie is found in the Law it selfe, wherein I will bee paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to cleare it to the people, and this is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly
<pb facs="tcp:176995:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:176995:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:176995:12"/>to be done in Parliament by aduice of the Iudges.</p>
            <p>The other corruption is introduced by the Iudges themselues, by Nicities that are vsed, where it may be said, <hi>Ab initio non fuit sic.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nothing in the world is more likely to bee permanent to our eyes then yron or steele, yet the rust corrupts it, if it bee not kept cleane: which sheweth nothing is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent here in this world, if it be not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: So I cannot discharge my conscience in maintayning the Lawes, if I keepe them not cleane from corruption.</p>
            <p>And now that I may be like the Pastour, that first takes the Sacrament himselfe, and then giues it to the people: So I haue first ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken my owne charge vpon me, before I giue you your Charge, lest it might bee said, <hi>Turpe est doctori, cum culpa redarguit ipsum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow my Lords the Iudges for your parts, the charge I haue to giue you, consists likewise in three parts.</p>
            <p>First in generall, that you doe Iustice vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly, as you shall answere to GOD, and
<pb facs="tcp:176995:12"/>mee: for as I haue onely GOD to answere to, and to expect punishment at his hands, if I offend; So you are to answere both to GOD and to mee, and expect punishment at GODS handes and mine, if you be found in fault.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to doe Iustice indifferently betweene Subiect and Subiect, betweene King and Subiect, without delay, partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, feare or briberie, with stoute and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right hearts, with cleane and vncorrupt handes.</p>
            <p>When I bid you doe Iustice boldly, yet I bid you doe it fearefully; fearefully in this, to vtter your owne conceits, and not the trew meaning of the Law: And remember you are no makers of Law, but Interpretours of Law, according to the trew sence thereof; for your Office is <hi>Ius dicere,</hi> and not <hi>Ius dare:</hi> And that you are so farre from making Law, that euen in the higher House of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament you haue no voice in making of a Law, but onely to giue your aduice when you are required.</p>
            <p>And though the Lawes bee in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:176995:13"/>obscure, and not so well knowne to the multitude as to you, and that there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny parts that come not into ordinary pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise, which are knowne to you, because you can finde out the reason thereof by bookes and presidents; yet know this, that your interpretations must bee alwayes sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to common sense and reason.</p>
            <p>For I will neuer trust any interpretation, that agreeth not with my common sense and reason, and trew Logicke: for <hi>Ratio est anima Legis</hi> in all humane Lawes, without exception; it must not bee Sophistrie or straines of wit that must interprete, but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cleare Law, or solide reason.</p>
            <p>But in Countreys where the formalitie of Law hath no place, as in <hi>Denmarke,</hi> which I may trewly report, as hauing my selfe bene an eye-witnesse thereof; all their State is gouerned onely by a written Law; there is no Aduocate or Proctour admitted to plead, onely the parties themselues plead their owne cause, and then a man stands vp and reads the Law, and there is an end; for the very Law-booke it selfe is their onely
<pb facs="tcp:176995:13"/>Iudge. Happy were all Kingdomes if they could be so: But heere, curious wits, vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conceits, different actions, and varietie of examples breed questions in Law: And therefore when you heare the questions, if they bee plaine, there is a plaine way in it selfe; if they bee such as are not plaine (for mens inuentions dayly abound) then are you to interprete according to common sense, and draw a good and certaine <hi>Minor</hi> of naturall reason, out of the <hi>Maior</hi> of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Lawe, and thereupon to make a right and trew <hi>Conclusion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For though the Common Law be a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie and skill best knowen vnto your selues, yet if your interpretation bee such, as other men which haue Logicke and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon sense vnderstand not the reason, I will neuer trust such an Interpretation.</p>
            <p>Remember also you are Iudges, and not a Iudge; and diuided into Benches, which sheweth that what you doe, that you should doe with aduice and deliberation, not hasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and rashly, before you well study the case, and conferre together; debating it duely,
<pb facs="tcp:176995:14"/>not giuing single opinions, <hi>per emendicata suffragia;</hi> and so to giue your Iudgement, as you will answer to God and me.</p>
            <p>Now hauing spoken of your Office in generall, I am next to come to the limits wherein you are to bound your selues, which likewise are three. First, Incroach not vpon the Prerogatiue of the Crowne: If there fall out a question that concernes my Prerogatiue or mystery of State, deale not with it, till you consult with the King or his Councell, or both: for they are tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scendent matters, and must not be sliberely caried with ouer-rash wilfulnesse; for so may you wound the King through the sides of a priuate person: and this I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vnto your speciall care, as some of you of late haue done very well, to blunt the sharpe edge and vaine popular humour of some Lawyers at the Barre, that thinke they are not eloquent and bold spirited e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, except they meddle with the Kings Prerogatiue: But doe not you suffer this; for certainly if this liberty bee suffered, the Kings Prerogatiue, the Crowne, and I, shall
<pb facs="tcp:176995:14"/>be as much wounded by their pleading, as if you resolued what they disputed: That which concernes the mysterie of the Kings power, is not lawfull to bee disputed; for that is to wade into the weakenesse of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to take away the mysticall reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that belongs vnto them that sit in the Throne of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That you keepe your selues within your owne Benches, not to inuade other Iurisdictions, which is vnfit, and an vnlawfull thing; In this I must inlarge my selfe. Besides the Courts of Common Law, there is the Court of Requests; the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raltie Court; the Court of the President and Councell of Walles, the President and Councell of the North; High Commission Courts, euery Bishop in his owne Court.</p>
            <p>These Courts ought to keepe their owne limits and boundes of their Commission and Instructions, according to the ancient Presidents: And like as I declare that my pleasure is, that euery of these shall keepe their owne limits and boundes; So the Courts of Common Lawe are not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croach
<pb facs="tcp:176995:15"/>vpon them, no more then it is my pleasure that they should encroach vpon the Common Law. And this is a thing Regall, and proper to a King, to keepe euery Court within his owne bounds.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Westminster</hi> Hal there are foure Courts: Two that handle causes Ciuil, which are the Common-pleas, and the Exchequer: Two that determine causes Criminall, which are the Kings-Bench, and the Starre-Chamber, where now I sit. The Common-Pleas is a part and branch of the Kings-Bench; for it was first all one Court; and then the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Pleas being extracted, it was called Common-Pleas; because it medled with the Pleas of Priuate persons, and that which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained, the Kings-Bench. The other of the Courts for ciuill Causes, is the Exchequer, which was ordeined for the Kings Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new: That is the principall Institution of that Court, and ought to be their chiefe studie; and as other things come orderly thither by occasion of the former, they may bee handled, and Iustice there administred.</p>
            <p>Keepe you therefore all in your owne bounds, and for my part, I desire you to
<pb facs="tcp:176995:15"/>giue me no more right in my priuate Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue, then you giue to any Subiect; and therein I will bee acquiescent: As for the absolute Prerogatiue of the Crowne, that is no Subiect for the tongue of a Lawyer, nor is lawfull to be disputed.</p>
            <p>It is Athiesme and blasphemie to dispute what God can doe: good Christians con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent themselues with his will reuealed in his word. So, it is presumption and high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt in a Subiect, to dispute what a King can doe, or say that a King cannot doe this, or that; but rest in that which is the Kings reuealed will in his Law.</p>
            <p>The Kings-Bench is the principall Court for criminall causes, and in some respects it deales with ciuill causes.</p>
            <p>Then is there a Chancerie Court; this is a Court of Equitie, and hath power to deale likewise in Ciuill causes. It is called the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spenser of the Kings Conscience, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alwayes the intention of Lawe and Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice; not altering the Law, not making that blacke which other Courts made white, nor, <hi>èconuerso;</hi> But in this it exceeds other
<pb facs="tcp:176995:16"/>Courts, mixing Mercie with Iustice, where other Courts proceed only according to the strict rules of Law: And where the rigour of the Law in many cases will vndoe a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, there the Chancerie tempers the Law with equitie, and so mixeth Mercie with Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, as it preserues men from destruction.</p>
            <p>And thus (as before I tolde you) is the Kings Throne established by Mercie and Iustice.</p>
            <p>The Chancerie is vndependant of any other Court, and is onely vnder the King: There it is written <hi>Teste meipso;</hi> from that Court there is no Appeale. And as I am bound in my Conscience to maintaine eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Courts Iurisdiction, so especially this, and not suffer it to sustaine wrong; yet so to maintaine it, as to keepe it within the ownelimits, and free from corruption. My Chancellor that now is, I found him Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Seale, the same place in substance, although I gaue him the Stile of Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, and God hath kept him in it till now; and I pray God he may hold it long; and so I hope he will. He will beare me witnesse,
<pb facs="tcp:176995:16"/>I neuer gaue him other warrant, then to goe on in his Court according to Presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, warranted by Law in the time of the best gouerning Kings, and most learned Chancellors; These were the limits I gaue vnto him; beyond the same limits hee hath promised me he will neuer goe.</p>
            <p>And as hee hath promised mee to take no other Iurisdiction to himselfe, so it is my promise euer to maintaine this Iurisdiction in that Court: Therefore I speake this to vindicate that Court from misconceipt and contempt.</p>
            <p>It is the duetie of Iudges to punish those that seeke to depraue the proceedings of any the Kings Courts, and not to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them any way: And I must confesse I thought it an odious and inept speach, and it grieued me very much, that it should bee said in <hi>Westminster</hi> Hall, that a <hi>Premunire</hi> lay against the Court of the Chancery and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers there: how can the King grant a <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire</hi> against himselfe?</p>
            <p>It was a foolish, inept, and presumptuous attempt, and fitter for the time of some vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie
<pb facs="tcp:176995:17"/>King: vnderstand mee aright; I meane not, the Chancerie should exceede his limite; but on the other part, the King onely is to correct it, and none else: And therefore I was greatly abused in that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. For if any was wronged there, the complaint should haue come to me. None of you but will confesse you haue a King of reasonable vnderstanding, and willing to reforme; why then should you spare to complaine to me, that being the high way; and not goe the other by-way, and backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, in contempt of our Authority.</p>
            <p>And therefore sitting heere in a seate of Iudgement, I declare and command, that no man hereafter presume to sue a <hi>Premunire</hi> against the Chancery; which I may the more easily doe, because no <hi>Premunire</hi> can bee sued but at my suite: And I may iustly barre my selfe at mine owne pleasure.</p>
            <p>As all inundations come with ouerflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the bankes, and neuer come without great inconuenience, and are thought pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious by Astrologers in things to come: So is this ouerflowing the bankes of your
<pb facs="tcp:176995:17"/>Iurisdiction in it selfe inconuenient, and may proue prodigious to the State.</p>
            <p>Remember therefore, that hereafter you keepe within your limits and Iurisdictions. It is a speciall point of my Office to procure and command, that amongst Courts there be a concordance, and musicall accord; and it is your parts to obey, and see this kept: And, as you are to obserue the ancient Lawes and customes of <hi>England;</hi> so are you to keepe your selues within the bound of direct Law, or presidents; and of those, not euery snatched president, carped now here, now there, as it were running by the way; but such as haue neuer bene controuerted, but by the contrary, approued by common vsage, in times of best Kings, and by most learned Iudges.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Starre-Chamber</hi> Court hath bene likewise shaken of late, and the last yeere it had receiued a sore blow, if it had not bene assisted and caried by a few voices; The very name of <hi>Starre-Chamber,</hi> seemeth to procure a reuerence to the Court.</p>
            <p>I will not play the Criticke to descant on
<pb facs="tcp:176995:18"/>the name; It hath a name from heauen, a Starre placed in it; and a Starre is a glorious creature, and seated in a glorious place, next vnto the Angels. The <hi>Starre-Chamber</hi> is also glorious in substance; for in the compositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is of foure sorts of persons: The first two are Priuie Councellors and Iudges, the one by wisedome in matters of State; the other, by learning in matters of Law, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and order all things both according to Law and State: The other two sorts are Peeres of the Realme, and Bishops: The Peeres are there by reason of their greatnes, to giue authoritie to that Court: The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops because of their learning in Diuinitie, and the interest they haue in the good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the Church: And so, both the learning of both diuine and humane Law, and experience and practise in Gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are conioyned together in the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of this Court.</p>
            <p>There is no Kingdome but hath a Court of Equitie, either by it selfe, as is here in <hi>England,</hi> or else mixed, and incorporate in their Office that are Iudges in the Law, as it
<pb facs="tcp:176995:18"/>is in <hi>Scotland:</hi> But the order of <hi>England</hi> is much more perfect, where they are diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And as in case of Equitie, where the Law determines not clearely, there the Chancerie doeth determine, hauing Equitie belonging to it, which doeth belong to no other Court: So the <hi>Starre-Chamber</hi> hath that belonging to it, which belongs to no other Court: For in this Court Attempts are punishable, where other Courts punish onely facts; And also where the Law pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisheth facts easily, as in case of Riotts or Combates, there the <hi>Starre-Chamber</hi> punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in a higher degree; And also all combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of practises and conspiracies; And if the King be dishonoured or contemned in his Prerogatiue, it belongs most proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Peeres and Iudges of this Court to punish it: So then this Court being institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for so great causes, it is great reason it should haue great honour.</p>
            <p>Remember now how I haue taught you brotherly loue one toward another: For you know well, that as you are Iudges, you are all brethren, and your Courts are sisters.
<pb facs="tcp:176995:19"/>I pray you therefore, labour to keepe that sweete harmonie which is amongst those Sisters the <hi>Muses.</hi> What greater misery can there be to the Law, then contempt of the Law? and what readier way to contempt, then when questions come, what shall bee determined in this Court, and what in that? Whereupon two euils doe arise; The one, that men come not now to Courts of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, to heare matters of right pleaded, and decrees giuen accordingly, but onely out of a curiositie to heare questions of the iuris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions of Courts disputed, and to see the euent, what Court is like to preuaile aboue the other; And the other is, that the Pleas are turned from Court to Court in an end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse circular motion, as vpon <hi>Ixions</hi> wheele: And this was the reason why I found iust fault with that multitude of Prohibitions: for when a poore Minister had with long labour, and great expence of charge and time, gotten a sentence for his Tithes, then comes a Prohibition, and turnes him round from Court to Court, and so makes his cause immortall and endlesse; for by this
<pb facs="tcp:176995:19"/>vncertaintie of Iurisdiction amongest Courts, causes are scourged from Court to Court, and this makes the fruit of suits like <hi>Tantalus</hi> fruit, still neere the suiters lips, but can neuer come to tast it. And this in deed is a great delay of Iustice, and makes causes endlesse: Therefore the onely way to auoyd this, is for you to keepe your owne bounds, and nourish not the people in contempt of other Courts, but teach them reuerence to Courts in your publique speaches, both in your Benches and in your Circuits; So shall you bring them to a reuerence, both of GOD, and of the King.</p>
            <p>Keepe therefore your owne limits to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the King, towards other Courts, and towards other Lawes, bounding your selues within your owne Law, and make not new Law. Remember, as I said before, that you are Iudges, to declare, and not to make Law: For when you make a Decree neuer heard of before, you are Law-giuers, and not Law-tellers.</p>
            <p>I haue laboured to gather some Articles, like an <hi>Index expurgatorius,</hi> of nouelties new
<pb facs="tcp:176995:20"/>crept into the Law, and I haue it ready to be considered of: Looke to <hi>Plowdens</hi> Cases, and your old <hi>Responsa prudentum;</hi> if you finde it not there, then <hi>(ab initio non fuit sic)</hi> I must say with CHRIST, Away with the new polygamie, and maintaine the ancient Law pure and vndefiled, as it was before.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O the Auditory I haue but little to say, yet that little will not be ill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed to be said at this time.</p>
            <p>Since I haue now renewed and confirmed my resolution to maintaine my Oath, the Law and Iustice of the Land; So do I expect, that you my Subiects do submit yourselues as you ought, to the obseruance of that Law.</p>
            <p>And as I haue diuided the two former parts of my Charge; So will I diuide this your submission into three parts; for order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diuisions and methode, cause things bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be remembred.</p>
            <p>First in generall, that you giue due reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Law; and this generall diuides it selfe into three.</p>
            <p>First, not to sue, but vpon iust cause.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176995:20"/>
            <p> Secondly, being sued, and Iudgement passed against you, Acquiesce in the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and doe not tumultuate against it; and take example from me, whom you haue heard here protest, that when euer any De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree shall be giuen against me in my priuate right, betweene me and a Subiect, I will as humbly acquiesce, as the meanest man in the Land. Imitate me in this, for in euery Plea there are two parties, and Iudgement can be but for one, and against the other, so one must alwayes be displeased.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, doe not complaine and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune mee against Iudgements; for I holde this Paradoxe to be a good rule in gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that it is better for a King to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine an vniust Decree, then to question e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Decree and Iudgement, after the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of a sentence; for then suites shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue ende: Therefore as you come ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to the Law for Iustice, so bee satisfied and contented when Iudgement is past a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst you, and trouble not mee; but if you finde briberie or corruption, then come boldly: but when I say boldly, beware of
<pb facs="tcp:176995:21"/>comming to complaine, except you be very sure to prooue the iustice of your cause: O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise looke for <hi>Lex Talionis</hi> to bee execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon you; for your accusing of an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Iudge, deserues double punishment, in that you seeke to lay infamie vpon a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy person of that reuerent calling.</p>
            <p>And bee not tild on with your owne Lawyers tales, that say the cause is iust for their owne gaine; but beleeue the Iudges, that haue no hire but of me.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in your Pleas, presume not to meddle with things against the Kings Prerogatiue, or Honour: Some Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of late haue bene too bold this wayes; If you vse it, the Iudges will punish you, and if they suffer it, I must punish both them and you. Plead not vpon new Puritanicall straines, that make all things popular; but keepe you within the ancient Limits of Pleas.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, make not many changes from Court to Court: for hee that changeth Courts, shewes to mistrust the iustnesse of the cause. Goe to the right place, and the
<pb facs="tcp:176995:21"/>Court that is proper for your cause; change not thence, and submit your selues to the Iudgement giuen there.</p>
            <p>Thus hauing finished the charge to my selfe, the Iudges and the Auditorie, I am to craue your pardon if I haue forgotten any thing, or beene inforced to breake my Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode; for you must remember, I come not hither with a written Sermon: I haue no Bookes to reade it out of, and a long speach, manifold businesse, and a little leasure may well pleade pardon for any fault of memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; and trewly I know not if I haue forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten any thing or not.</p>
            <p>And now haue I deliuered, First my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse, why I came not till now: Next, the reasons why I came now: Thirdly, my charge, and that to my selfe, to you my Lords the Iudges, and to the Auditorie.</p>
            <p>I haue also an ordinarie charge that I vse to deliuer to the Iudges before my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, when they goe their circuits; and seeing I am come to this place, you shall haue that also, and so I will make the old saying trew, <hi>Combe seldome, combe sore,</hi> I meane by my
<pb facs="tcp:176995:22"/>long deteining you at this time, which will be so much the more profitable in this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditorie; because a number of the Auditorie will be informed here who may relate it to their fellow Iustices in the countrey.</p>
            <p>My Lords the Iudges, you know very well, that as you are Iudges with mee when you sit here; so are your Iudges vnder me, and my Substitutes in the circuits, where you are Iudges Itinerant to doe Iustice to my people.</p>
            <p>It is an ancient and laudable custome in this Kingdome, that the Iudges goe thorow the Kingdome in Circuits, easing the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple thereby of great charges, who must otherwise come from all the remote parts of the Kingdome to <hi>Westminster Hall,</hi> for the finding out and punishing of offences past, and preuenting the occasion of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that may arise.</p>
            <p>I can giue you no other charge in effect, but onely to remember you againe of the same in substance which I deliuered to you this time Twelue-moneth.</p>
            <p>First, remember that when you goe your
<pb facs="tcp:176995:22"/>Circuits, you goe not onely to punish and preuent offences, but you are to take care for the good gouernment in general of the parts where you trauell, as well as to doe Iustice in particular betwixt party and party, in causes criminall and ciuill.</p>
            <p>You haue charges to giue to Iustices of peace, that they doe their dueties when you are absent, aswell as present: Take an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of them, and report their seruice to me at your returne.</p>
            <p>As non of you will hold it sufficient to giue a charge, except in taking the accompt, you finde the fruit of it: So I say to you, it will not be sufficient for you, to heare my charge, if at your returne, you bring not an accompt to the haruest of my sowing, which cannot bee done in generall, but in making to me a particular report what you haue done.</p>
            <p>For, a King hath two Offices.</p>
            <p>First, to direct things to be done:</p>
            <p>Secondly, to take an accompt how they are fulfilled, for what is it the better for mee
<pb facs="tcp:176995:23"/>to direct as an Angel, if I take not accompt of your doings.</p>
            <p>I know not whether misunderstanding, or slackenesse bred this, that I had no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt but in generall, of that I gaue you in particular in charge the last yeere: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I now charge you againe, that at your next returne, you repaire to my <hi>Chancellor,</hi> and bring your accompts to him in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, of those things which in particular I haue giuen you in charge: And then when I haue seene your accompts, as occasion shall serue, it may bee I will call for some of you, to be informed of the state of that part of the countrey where your Circuit lay.</p>
            <p>Of these two parts of your seruice, I know the ordinary legall part of <hi>Nisiprius</hi> is the more profitable to you: But the other part of iustice is more necessary for my fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. Therefore as <hi>Christ</hi> said to the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, <hi>Hoc agite,</hi> as the most principall: yet I wil say, <hi>Et illud non omittite:</hi> which, that you may the better doe, I haue allowed you a day more in your Circuits, then my Predeces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors haue done.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176995:23"/>
            <p> And this you shall finde, that euen as a King, (let him be neuer so godly, wise, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and iust) yet if the sublaterne Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strats doe not their parts vnder him, the Kingdome must needes suffer: So let the Iudges be neuer so carefull and industrious, if the Iustices of Peace vnder them, put not to their helping handes, in vaine is all your labour: For they are the Kings eyes and eares in the countrey. It was an ancient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome, that all the Iudges both immediatly before their going to their Circuits, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly vpon their returne, repaired to the Lord <hi>Chancellour</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> both to receiue what directions it should please the King by his mouth to giue vnto them; as also to giue him an accompt of their labours, who was to acquaint the King therewith: And this good ancient custome hath likewise beene too much slacked of late; And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore first of all, I am to exhort &amp; command you, that you bee carefull to giue a good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt to mee and my <hi>Chancellor,</hi> of the due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties performed by all Iustices of Peace in your Circuits: Which gouernment by Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices,
<pb facs="tcp:176995:24"/>is so lawdable and so highly esteemed by mee, that I haue made <hi>Scotland</hi> to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned by iustices and Constables, as <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is. And let not Gentlemen be ashamed of this Place; for it is a place of high Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and great reputation, to bee made a Minister of the Kings Iustice, in seruice of the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>Of these there are two sorts, as there is of all Companies, especially where there is a great number; that is, good and bad Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: For the good, you are to informe me of them, that I may know them, thanke them, and reward them, as occasion serues: For I hold a good Iustice of Peace in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, to doe mee as good seruice, as hee that waits vpon me in my Priuie Chamber, and as ready will I be to reward him; For I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt him as capable of any Honour, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, or preferrement about my Person, or for any place of Councell or State, as well as any Courteour that is neere about mee, or any that haue deserued well of me in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine imployments: Yea I esteeme the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice done mee by a good Iustice of Peace,
<pb facs="tcp:176995:24"/>three hundred miles, yea sixe hundred miles out of my sight, as well as the seruice done me in my presence: For as God hath giuen mee large limits, so must I bee carefull that my prouidence may reach to the farthest parts of them: And as Law cannot bee ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, except Honour be giuen to Iudges: so without due respect to Iustices of Peace, what regard will be had of the seruice?</p>
            <p>Therefore let none bee ashamed of this Office, or be discouraged in being a Iustice of Peace, if he serue worthily in it.</p>
            <p>The Chancellour vnder me, makes Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and puts them out; but neither I, nor hee can tell what they are: Therefore wee must be informed by you Iudges, who can onely tell, who doe well, and who doe ill; without which, how can the good bee che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished and maintained, and the rest put out? The good Iustices are carefull to attend the seruice of the King and countrey, for thanks onely of the King, and loue to their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and for no other respect.</p>
            <p>The bad are either idle Slowbellies, that abide alwayes at home, giuen to a life of ease
<pb facs="tcp:176995:25"/>and delight, liker Ladies then men; and thinke it is enough to contemplate Iustice, when as <hi>Virtus in actione consistit:</hi> contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>platiue Iustice is no iustice, and contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Iustices are fit to be put out.</p>
            <p>Another sort of Iustices are busie-bodies, and will haue all men dance after their pipe, and follow their greatnesse, or else will not be content; A sort of men, <hi>Quise primos om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium esse putant, nec sunt tamen:</hi> these proud spirits must know, that the countrey is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to obey and follow GOD and the King, and not them.</p>
            <p>Another sort are they, that goe seldome to the Kings seruice, but when it is to helpe some of their kindred or alliance; So as when they come, it is to helpe their friends, or hurt their enemies, making Iustice to serue for a shadow to Faction, and tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuating the countrey.</p>
            <p>Another sort are Gentlemen of great worth in their owne conceit, and cannot bee content with the present forme of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, but must haue a kind of libertie in the people, and must bee gracious Lords,
<pb facs="tcp:176995:25"/>and Redeemers of their libertie; and in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery cause that concernes Prerogatiue, giue a snatch against a Monarchie, through their Puritanical it ching after Popularitie: Some of them haue shewed themselues too bold of late in the lower house of Parliament: And when all is done, if there were not a King, they would be lesse cared for then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men.</p>
            <p>And now hauing spoken of the qualities of the Iustices of Peace; I am next to speake of their number. As I euer held the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in all things to be the way of Vertue, in eschewing both extremities: So doe I in this: for vpon the one part, a multitude of Iustices of Peace in the countrey more then is necessary, breeds but confusion for although it be an old Prouerbe, that <hi>Many handes make light worke;</hi> yet too many make slight worke; and too great a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Iustices of Peace, will make the busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the countrey to bee the more neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, euery one trusting to another, so as nothing shalbe well done; besides the bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of great corruption: for where there
<pb facs="tcp:176995:26"/>is a great number, it can hardly be, but some wilbe corrupted. And vpon the other part, too few Iustices of Peace, will not be able to vndergoe the burthen of the seruice; And therefore I would neither haue too few, nor too many, but as many in euery countrey, as may, according to the proportion of that countrey, bee necessary for the performing of the seruice there, and no more.</p>
            <p>As to the charge you are to giue to the Iustices, I can but repeat what formerly I haue told you; Yet in so good a businesse, <hi>Lectio lecta placet, decies repetita placebit.</hi> And as I beganne with fulfilling the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe, <hi>A Ioue principium;</hi> so will I beginne the charge you haue to giue to the Iustices with Church-matters: for GOD will blesse euery good businesse the better, that he and his Church haue the precedence. That which I am now to speake, is anent Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sants and Papists. You neuer returned from any Circuit, but by your accompt made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, I both conceiued great comfort, and great griefe: Comfort, when I heard a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Recusants in some Circuits to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minished:
<pb facs="tcp:176995:26"/>Griefe to my heart and soule, when I heard a number of Recusants to be in other Circuits increased.</p>
            <p>I protest vnto you, nothing in the earth can grieue mee so much, as mens falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from Religion in my dayes; And no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing so much ioyes me, as when that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion increaseth vnder mee. GOD is my witnesse, I speake nothing for vaine-glory; but speake it againe; My heart is grieued when I heare Recusants increase: Therefore I wish you Iudges, to take it to heart, as I doe, and preuent it as you can; and make mee knowen to my people, as I am.</p>
            <p>There are three sorts of Recusants: The first are they that for themselues will bee no Recusants, but their wiues and their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies are; and they themselues doe come to Church, but once or twice in a yeere, infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by Law, or for fashion sake; These may bee formall to the Law, but more false to GOD then the other sort.</p>
            <p>The second sort are they that are Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sants &amp; haue their conscience misse-led, and therefore refuse to come to Church, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise
<pb facs="tcp:176995:27"/>liue as peaceable Subiects.</p>
            <p>The third sort are practising Recusants: These force all their seruants to bee Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sants with them; they will suffer none of their tenants, but they must be Recusants; and their neighbours if they liue by them in peace, must be Recusants also.</p>
            <p>These you may finde out as a foxe by the foule smell, a great way round about his hole; This is a high pride and presumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they for whose soules I must an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere to GOD, and who enioy their liues and liberties vnder mee, will not onely bee Recusants themselues, but infect and draw others after them.</p>
            <p>As I haue said in Parliament house, I can loue the person of a Papist, being otherwise a good man and honestly bred, neuer ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing knowen any other Religion: but the person of an Apostate Papist, I hate. And surely for those Polypragmaticke Papists, I would you would studie out some seuere punishment for them: for they keepe not infection in their owne hearts onely, but also infect others our good Subiects. And
<pb facs="tcp:176995:27"/>that which I say for Recusants, the same I say for Priests: I confesse I am loath to hang a Priest onely for Religion sake, and saying Masse; but if he refuse the Oath of Alleagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance (which, let the Pope and all the deuils in Hell say what they will) yet (as you finde by my booke and by diuers others, is meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ciuill) those that so refuse the Oath, and are Polypragmaticke Recusants; I leaue them to the Law; it is no persecution, but good Iustice.</p>
            <p>And those Priests also, that out of my Grace and Mercy haue beene let goe out of prisons, and banished, vpon condition not to returne; aske mee no questions touching these, quit me of them, and let me not heare of them. And to them I ioyne those that breake prison; for such Priests as the prison will not hold, it is a plaine signe nothing will hold them but a halter: Such are no Martyrs that refuse to suffer for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science. <hi>Paul,</hi> notwithstanding the doores were open, would not come foorth. And <hi>Peter</hi> came not out of the prison till led by the Angell of God: But these will goe forth
<pb facs="tcp:176995:28"/>though with the angell of the Diuell.</p>
            <p>I haue giuen order to my Lord of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> and my Lord of <hi>London</hi> for the distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, &amp;c. of the degrees of Priestes; and when I haue an accompt from them, then will I giue you another charge concerning them.</p>
            <p>Another thing that offendeth the Realme, is abundance of Ale-houses; and therefore to auoyd the giuing occasion of euill, and to take away the roote, and punish the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of vice, I would haue the infamous Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houses pulled downe, and a command to all Iustices of Peace that this be done.</p>
            <p>I may complaine of Ale-houses, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of Stealers of my Deere; but the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey may complaine for stealing their hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, oxen, and sheepe; for murder, cutting of purses, and such like offences; for these are their haunts. Deuouring beasts, as Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Beares, will not be where they haue no dennes nor couert, So there would be no theeues, if they had not their receipts, and these Alehouses as their dennes.</p>
            <p>Another sort, are a kinde of Ale-houses,
<pb facs="tcp:176995:28"/>which are houses of haunt and receipt for debaushed rogues and vagabonds, and idle sturdie fellowes; and these are not properly Ale houses, but base victuallers, such as haue nothing else to liue by, but keeping houses of receipt for such kinde of custo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers. I haue discouered a strange packe of late, That within tenne or twelue miles of London, there are tenne or twelue persons that liue in spight of me; going with Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stols, and walking vp and downe from har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to harbour killing my Deere, and so shift from hold to hold, that they cannot be apprehended.</p>
            <p>For Rogues, you haue many good Acts of Parliament: <hi>Edward</hi> the sixt, though hee were a child, yet for this, he in his time gaue better order then many Kings did in their aage: You must take order for these Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars and Rogues; for they so swarme in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery place, that a man cannot goe in the streetes, nor in the high wayes, nor any where for them.</p>
            <p>Looke to your houses of Correction, and remember that in the chiefe Iustice
<pb facs="tcp:176995:29"/>
               <hi>Pophams</hi> time, there was not a wandering begger to be found in all <hi>Somersetshire,</hi> being his natiue countrey.</p>
            <p>Haue a care also to suppresse the building of Cottages vpon Commons, which are as bad as Alehouses, and the dwellers in them do commonly steale Deare, connies, sheepe, oxen, horses, breake houses, and doe all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of villanies. It is trew, some ill Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces make gaine of these base things take an accompt of the Iustices of Peace, that they may know they doe these things against the will of the King.</p>
            <p>I am likewise to commend vnto you a thing very necessarie, High-wayes and Bridges; because no Common-weale can bee without passage: I protest, that as my heart doeth ioy in the erection of Schooles and Hospitals, which haue bene more in my time, then in many aages of my prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors; so it grieues me, and it is wonderfull to see the decay of charitie in this; how scant men are in contributing towards the amendment of High-wayes and Bridges: Therefore take a care of this, for that is
<pb facs="tcp:176995:29"/>done to day with a penie, that will not bee done hereafter with an hundred pounds, and that will bee mended now in a day, which hereafter will not bee mended in a yeere; and that in a yeere, which will not be done in our time, as wee may see by <hi>Paules</hi> Steeple.</p>
            <p>Another thing to be cared for, is, the new Buildings here about the Citie of London; concerning which my Proclamations haue gone foorth, and by the chiefe Iustice here, and his Predecessor <hi>Popham,</hi> it hath bene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solued to bee a generall nusans to the whole Kingdome: And this is that, which is like the Spleene in the body, which in measure as it ouergrowes, the body wastes. For is it possible but the countrey must diminish, if London doe so increase, and all sorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple doe come to London? and where doeth this increase appeare? not in the heart of the City, but in the suburbs; not giuing wealth or profit to the City, but bringing miserie and surcharge both to City and Court; cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing dearth and scarsitie through the great prouision of victuals and fewell, that must
<pb facs="tcp:176995:30"/>be for such a multitude of people And these buildings serue likewise to harbor the worst sort of people, as Alehouses and cottages doe. I remember, that before Christmas was twelue-moneth I made a Proclamation for this cause, That all Gentlemen of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie should depart to their owne countreys and houses, to maintaine hospitalitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst their neighbours; which was equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocally taken by some, as that it was meant onely for that Christmas: But my will and meaning was, and here I declare that my meaning was, that it should alwayes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue.</p>
            <p>One of the great causes of all Gentlemens desire, that haue no calling or errand, to dwell in London, is apparently the pride of the women: For if they be wiues, then their husbands; and if they be maydes, then their fathers must bring them vp to London, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the new fashion is to be had no where but in London: and here, if they be vnmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, they marre their marriages, and if they be married, they loose their reputations, and robbe their husbands purses. It is the fashi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:176995:30"/>of <hi>Italy,</hi> especially of <hi>Naples,</hi> (which is one of the richest parts of it) that all the Gentry dwell in the principall townes, and so the whole countrey is emptie: Euen so now in <hi>England,</hi> all the countrey is gotten into <hi>London;</hi> so as with time, <hi>England</hi> will onely bee <hi>London,</hi> and the whole countrey be left waste: For as we now do imitate the French fashion, in fashion of Clothes, and Lackeys to follow euery man; So haue wee got vp the Italian fashion, in liuing misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in our houses, and dwelling all in the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: but let vs in Gods name leaue these idle forreine toyes, and keepe the old fashion of <hi>England:</hi> For it was wont to bee the honour and reputation of the English Nobilitie and Gentry, to liue in the countrey, and keepe hospitalitie; for which wee were famous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all the countreys in the world; which we may the better doe, hauing a soile abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly fertile to liue in.</p>
            <p>And now out of my owne mouth I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare vnto you, which being in this place, is equall to a Proclamation, which I intend likewise shortly hereafter to haue publikely
<pb facs="tcp:176995:31"/>proclaimed,) that the Courtiers, Citizens, and Lawyers, and those that belong vnto them, and others as haue Pleas in Terme time, are onely necessary persons to remaine about this City; others must get them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the countrey, For beside the hauing of the countrey desolate, when the Gentrie dwell thus in LONDON, diuers other mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes arise vpon it: First, if insurrections should fall out (as was lately seene by the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellers gathering together) what order can be taken with it, when the countrey is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furnished of Gentlemen to take order with it? Next, the poore want reliefe for fault of the Gentlemens hospitality at home: Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, my seruice is neglected, and the good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the countrey for lacke of the principall Gentlemens presence, that should performe it: And lastly, the Gentlemen lose their owne thrift, for lacke of their owne presence, in seeing to their owne bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sines at home. Therefore as euery fish liues in his owne place, some in the fresh, some in the salt, some in the mud: so let euery one liue in his owne place, some at Court, some
<pb facs="tcp:176995:31"/>in the Citie, some in the Countrey; specially at Festiuall times, as Christmas and Easter, and the rest.</p>
            <p>And for the decrease of new buildings heere, I would haue the builders restrained, and committed to prison; and if the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders cannot be found, then the workemen to bee imprisoned; and not this onely, but likewise the buildings to bee cast downe; I meane such buildings as may bee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen without inconuenience, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that to be done by order and direction.</p>
            <p>There may be many other abuses that I know not of, take you care my Lords the Iudges of these, and of all other; for it is your part to looke vnto them. I heare say, robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry begins to abound more then heretofore, and that some of you are too mercifull; I pray you remember, that mercy is the Kings, not yours, and you are to doe Iustice where trew cause is: And take this for a rule of Policie, That what vice most a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds in a Common wealth, that must bee most seuerely punished; for that is trew gouernment.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176995:32"/>
            <p> And now I wil conclude my Speach with GOD, as I began. First, that in all your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiours, aswell in your Circuits as in your Benches, you giue due reuerence to God: I meane, let not the Church nor Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men be disgraced in your Charges, nor Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists nor Puritanes countenanced: Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and encourage the good Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and teach the people by your exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to reuerence them: for, if they be good, they are worthy of double honour for their Office sake; if they bee faultie, it is not your place to admonish them; they haue ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Forum</hi> to answere to for their misbeha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour.</p>
            <p>Next, procure reuerence to the King and the Law; informe my people trewly of me, how zealous I am for Religion, howl desire Law may be maintained and flourish; that euery Court should haue his owne Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction; that euery Subiect should submit himselfe to Law; So may you liue a happy people vnder a Iust KING, freely enioying the fruit of PEACE and IVSTICE, as such a people should doe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176995:32"/>
            <p> Now I confesse, it is but a <hi>Tandem aliquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> as they say in the Schooles, that I am come hither: Yet though this be the first, it shall not, with the grace of God, be the last time of my comming, now my choice is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away; for hauing once bene here, a meaner occasion may bring mee againe: And I hope I haue euer caried my selfe so, and by Gods grace euer will, as none will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersuspect, that my comming here will bee to any partiall end; for I will euer bee care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in point of Iustice, to keepe my selfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spotted all the dayes of my life. And vpon this my generall protestation, I hope the world wil know, that I came hither this day to maintaine the Law, and doe Iustice according to my Oath.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176995:33"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176995:33"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>